# Qincheng (Daisy) Lu

School of Computer Science, McGill University, Montreal, QC <a href="mailto:qincheng.lu@mail.mcgill.ca">qincheng.lu@mail.mcgill.ca</a> | LinkedIn | Google scholar | 1-778-3503505 | Canadian citizen

## **Highlights**

I am a PhD candidate specializing in representation learning for graph and time-series, developing machine learning methods for integer parameter estimation in linear models and combinatorial optimization, with applications in wireless communications, signal processing and GNSS based positioning.

My expertise includes:

- **Graph Neural Network**: graph spectral theory, heterophilic learning
- **Deep Generative Models:** VAE, diffusion models
- Time-series Representation Learning: Transformer, SSM, neural ODE

### **Skills**

- **Programming Language:** Python, R, MATLAB, C, C++, Java, SQL
- Computing Libraries: NumPy, SciPy, Pandas, Scikit-learn, PyTorch, TensorFlow

#### **Education**

•	Ph.D. Computer Science, 4.0/4.0	09/2020 - Flexible
	School of Computer Science, McGill University, Montreal, Canada Advisor: Xiao-Wen Chang	
•	M.Sc. Statistics, 90.8/100 (A+)	09/2018 - 08/2020
	Dept. of Mathematics and Statistics, University of Victoria, Victoria, Canada Advisor: Xuekui Zhang	
•	LLB, 3.64/4.0   Minor in Data Science, School of Computer Science, 3.6/4.0	09/2014 - 06/2018
	Fudan University, Shanghai, China	

# **Professional Experience**

• Co-op Student - BC Ministry of Health

- 01/2020 05/2020
- o Developed a Shiny application served as a data center for analyzing and reporting.
- o Automated data collection and data quality evaluation using R language.
- o Significantly improved the data analysis efficiency for the team.
- Developer Google Summer of Code, R Project for Statistical Computing

05/2019 - 08/2019

- o Implemented five new optimization methods in C++ and extended test cases in R.
- o Employed the SAGA algorithm with optimal batch/step size and cache locality.
- o Proposed new algorithms for non-convex penalty and not-Lipschitz-continuous derivative.
- SDE Intern Dell EMC Shanghai R&D Center

02/2018 - 09/2018

- o Developed a web application connecting Avamar servers using Django, Paramiko, and SQLite3.
- o Implemented test strategies for installation, upgrade, and hotfix for multiple releases of Avamar.
- o Managed cluster network for DPSearch team, developed and extended tools for internal usage.
- Mitacs Globalink Research Intern-University of Victoria, Dept. of Economics 06/2017-09/201
  - o Built an analytics pipeline for text mining and text data pre-processing for research using STATA.

#### **Activities**

•	Lecturer of Numerical Computing to over 200 students at McGill University	Fall 2021, 2023
•	Organizer of LoG 2023 Montreal Meetup, presented tutorial for LoG 2024	2023, 2024

## **Research Experience**

• **PhD Research Assistant - McGill University** 

09/2020 - Present

- Graph Neural Network
  - o Proposed the graph convolution-enhanced expectation propagation network to infer the integer parameters in linear models for MIMO detection. Published at GLOBECOM 2024.
  - o Proposed the flexible diffusion with parameterized Laplacian. Published at LoG 2024 (PMLR).
  - Conducted research on the modeling and theoretical analysis for heterophilic-specific Graph Neural Network. Published at NeurIPS 2022, 2023.

#### Generative AI

- o Proposed a VAE for parameter estimation in integer least squares problem. Published at ISIT 2023.
- Conducted research on diffusion models to generate solutions for unconstrained integer linear system to resolve the integer ambiguities in GPS positioning. Ongoing.
- o Developed foundation models for time-series forecasting using generative pre-training on biosignals and longitudinal medical data. Published at MLHC (PMLR), ACM BCB, NeurIPS TSALM, 2024.
- Master Research Assistant University of Victoria

09/2018 - 08/2020

o Conducted research on a non-parametric approach for detecting differentially expressed genes on scRNAseq data with an abundance of zero and multimodality.

#### **Publications**

- 1. *Q. Lu*, S. Luan, and X.-W. Chang. GCEPNet: Graph Convolution-Enhanced Expectation Propagation for Massive MIMO Detection. To Appear in Proceedings of the 2024 IEEE Global Communications Conference (GLOBECOM).
- 2. *Q. Lu*, J. Zhu, S. Luan, and X.-W. Chang. Flexible Diffusion Scopes with Parameterized Laplacian for Heterophilic Graph Learning. To Appear in the Proceeding of Machine Learning Research (PMLR) for Learning on Graphs Conference (LoG), 2024.
- 3. Z. Song, *Q. Lu*, H. Zhu, and Y. Li. Bidirectional Generative Pre-training for Improving Time-series Representation Learning. To Appear in Proceedings of the 9th Machine Learning for Healthcare Conference (MLHC) and the Proceeding of Machine Learning Research (PMLR), 2024.
- 4. Z. Song, *Q. Lu*, H. Xu, and Y. Li. TimelyGPT: Extrapolatable Transformer Pre-training for Long-term Time-series Forecasting in Healthcare. To Appear in ACM Conference on Bioinformatics, Computational Biology, and Health Informatics (ACM-BCB), 2024.
- 5. Z. Song, *Q. Lu*, H. Zhu, D. L. Buckeridge, and Y. Li. TrajGPT: Healthcare Time-series Representation Learning for Trajectory Prediction. In NeurIPS Workshop on Time Series in the Age of Large Models, 2024.
- 6. S. Luan, C. Hua, *Q. Lu*, L. Ma, L. Wu, X. Wang, M. Xu, X.-W. Chang, D. Precup, R. Ying, et al. The Heterophilic Graph Learning Handbook: Benchmarks, Models, Theoretical Analysis, Applications and Challenges. arXiv preprint arXiv:2407.09618, 2024.
- 7. S. Luan, C. Hua, M. Xu, *Q. Lu*, J. Zhu, X.-W. Chang, J. Fu, J. Leskovec, and D. Precup. When Do Graph Neural Networks Help with Node Classification? Investigating the Homophily Principle on Node Distinguishability. Proceedings of NeurIPS 2023.
- 8. X.-W. Chang, *Q. Lu*, and Y. Xu. Success Probabilities of L2-norm Regularized Babai Detectors and Maximization. Proceedings of the 2023 IEEE International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT).
- 9. X.-W. Chang, *Q. Lu*. A Machine Learning-based Method for Resolving GNSS Integer Ambiguities. 2023 International Congress on Industrial and Applied Mathematics, Talk.
- 10. S. Luan, C. Hua, *Q. Lu*, J. Zhu, M. Zhao, S. Zhang, X.-W. Chang, and D. Precup. Revisiting Heterophily for Graph Neural Networks. Proceedings of NeurIPS 2022, Spotlight.